The next group of operators is the
group that is probably most familiar,
and that is the arithmetic group. To focus
more on the operators, we will forego the
gaming examples in this code and strictly focus
on arithmetic operators. We see this code in
this 144-arithmetic code file. This code example
has two variables, x, and y, on lines 1 and 2,
and then several calculations using these two
variables. I will comment out the print statement
on line 18, as that has an order of operations
factor we want to look at separately. If you
have done any work on computers, the first
four print statements, lines 4 through 10,
should have operators that look familiar to
you. I will run this code to get some answers,
and then we will go back and evaluate these print
statements. The first four print statements add,
subtract, multiply, and divide x and y; we see the
first four results here in the terminal. Notice
that with Python, dividing two integers does not
always render an integer, as with many programming
languages. Python implicitly converts a result to
a float, as we see with 5/3 equaling 1.66666667
or, one and two-thirds. Lines 12, 14, and 16 have
what some would consider to be some of the more
unfamiliar operators in Python. The double slash
on line 12 indicates a floor division operator,
which returns just the integer portion of an
answer. Five divided by three without a decimal
is 1. The next operator, on line 14, the percent
symbol, is the modulus operator, which shows the
remainder after a division between two numbers.
5 divided by 3 is 1 with a remainder of 2. Thus,
2 is the modulus, and the result shows here.
On line 16, we see two asterisks. In Python,
a double asterisk indicates an exponent,
or, as some refer, to the power of. Thus,
line 16 is 5 to the power of 3, which is
5 * 5 * 5 which equals this result: 125.